<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.3//EN"
"/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
-->
<appendix id="molecule-formats">
  <title>Molecule Formats</title>

  <para>The <emphasis>Molecule Formats</emphasis> appendix describes the file
  formats supported by the Mychem software. Further informations about
  chemical file formats are available on <ulink
  url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chemical_file_format">Wikipedia</ulink>.</para>

  <sect1 id="serialized.obmol">
    <title>Serialized OBMol</title>

    <para>The serialized OBMol format is a bit string obtained by serializing
    an OBMol object. This type of string stores most of the data contained in
    a OBMol object, with exception to 2D and 3D coordinates. The binary
    structure of this string is described on the <ulink
    url="http://chemdb.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/Binary_storage_of_OBMol_objects_for_faster_operations">ChemiSQL
    Website</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="cml">
    <title>CML</title>

    <para>The Chemical Markup Language (CML) is an open standard for
    representing molecular structures, as well as many other types of chemical
    data. It is based on the XML language and can be simply processed by any
    XML parser. The <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/cml/">CML
    Project Website</ulink>, hosts the XML Schema and source codes for parsing
    and working with CML data.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="fingerprints">
    <title>Fingerprints</title>

    <para>This section presents fingerprint types used by the Mychem software.
    Further details about fingerprints are given in an <ulink
    url="http://www.dalkescientific.com/writings/diary/archive/2008/06/26/fingerprint_background.html">article</ulink>
    written by Andrew Dalke. In short, fingerprints are a bit string
    representation of a molecule. Most of them can be classified in two
    categories:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Structural fingerprint - This fingerprint type is based on
        substructure features.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hash fingerprints - This fingerprint type is a hash of the
        representation of a molecule. It is used most often in similarity
        searching, with the hypothesis that two similar compounds create
        similar fingerprints, and that two similar fingerprints means the
        compounds are similar.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2 id="fingerprints.fp2">
      <title>FP2</title>

      <para>FP2 fingerprints index small molecule fragments based on linear
      segments of up to 7 atoms in length. They are hash fingerprints. The
      specification of the FP2 fingerprints is available on the <ulink
      url="http://openbabel.org/wiki/FP2">Open Babel Website</ulink>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="fingerprints.fp3">
      <title>FP3</title>

      <para>FP3 fingerprints index small molecule fragments based on a list of
      SMART patterns. They are hash fingerprints. The SMART patterns are
      listed in the file named <filename>patterns.txt</filename>, that is
      distributed with the Open Babel software. The specification of the FP3
      fingerprints is available on the <ulink
      url="http://openbabel.org/wiki/FP3">Open Babel Website</ulink>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="fingerprints.fp4">
      <title>FP4</title>

      <para>FP4 fingerprints index small molecule fragments based on a list of
      SMART patterns. They are hash fingerprints. The SMART patterns are
      listed in the file named <filename>SMARTS_InteLigand.txt</filename>,
      that is distributed with the Open Babel software. The specification of
      the FP4 fingerprints is available on the <ulink
      url="http://openbabel.org/wiki/FP4">Open Babel Website</ulink>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="inchi">
    <title>InChI</title>

    <para>The IUPAC International Chemical Identifier (InChI) is an identifier
    for chemical substances that can be used in printed and electronic data
    sources. It was developed under IUPAC Project 2000-025-1-800. Details of
    the project are available from the <ulink
    url="http://www.iupac.org/inchi">IUPAC Website</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mol2">
    <title>Sybyl Mol2</title>

    <para>The Sybyl Mol2 format is a complete, portable representation of a
    molecule. It is an ASCII file that contains structural data as well as
    Sybyl related data (Sybyl is a chemoinformatics software released by
    Tripos). The file format is described on the <ulink
    url="http://www.tripos.com/data/support/mol2.pdf">Tripos
    Website</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="molfile">
    <title>MDL Molfile</title>

    <para>A MDL Molfile is a file format created by MDL for holding data about
    the atoms, bonds, connectivity and coordinates of a molecule. This file
    format consists of some header information, the Connection Table (CT)
    containing atom info, then bond connections and types, followed by
    sections for more complex information. The format is described on the
    <ulink url="http://www.mdli.com/downloads/public/ctfile/ctfile.jsp">MDLI
    Website</ulink>. There is two versions of MDL Molfile:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>V2000</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>V3000</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2 id="molfile.v2000">
      <title>V2000</title>

      <para>It is the current standard. However, it presents a limitation, as
      it support up to 999 atoms or bonds.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="molfile.v3000">
      <title>V3000</title>

      <para>The V3000 format has been created to support more than 999 atoms
      or bonds. It can be useful for describing proteins and polymers.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="pdb">
    <title>PDB</title>

    <para>The Protein Data Bank Format is commonly used for proteins and
    biological macromolecules. It was originally designed as a
    fixed-column-width format and thus officially has a built-in maximum
    number of atoms; however, many tools can read files that exceed the limit.
    Some PDB files contain an optional section describing atom connectivity as
    well as position. Further informations about this format can be retrieved
    from the <ulink url="http://www.wwpdb.org/docs.html">PDB
    Website</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="smiles">
    <title>SMILES</title>

    <para>The Simplified Molecular Input Line Entry Specification (SMILES)
    format is a linear text format which can describe the connectivity and
    chirality of a molecule. It does not include 2D or 3D coordinates and
    hydrogens atoms are not represented. The SMILES are described on the
    <ulink url="http://www.daylight.com/smiles/">Daylight Website</ulink>.
    However, a complete SMILES standard does not exist. Craig James is leading
    a campaign to develop an Open Standard for SMILES. The discussion is
    taking place under the umbrella of the <ulink
    url="http://blueobelisk.sourceforge.net/wiki/Open_Standard_for_SMILES">Blue
    Obelisk Group</ulink>.</para>

    <sect2 id="smiles.canonical">
      <title>Canonical SMILES</title>

      <para>Canonical SMILES is a particular type of SMILES, that has a single
      <emphasis>canonical</emphasis> form for any particular molecule,
      regardless of atom order.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
