<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.4//EN"
                      "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY introduction SYSTEM "introduction.xml">
<!ENTITY usingMychem SYSTEM "using-mychem.xml">
<!ENTITY commandReference SYSTEM "command-reference.xml">
<!ENTITY credits SYSTEM "credits.xml">
<!ENTITY installation SYSTEM "installation.xml">
<!ENTITY troubleshooting SYSTEM "troubleshooting.xml">
<!ENTITY sdfscript SYSTEM "sdfscript.xml">
<!ENTITY db-manager SYSTEM "db-manager.xml">
<!ENTITY molecule.formats SYSTEM "molecule-formats.xml">
]>
<!-- "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" -->
<book id="mychem" lang="en">

<bookinfo>

  <title>The Mychem Handbook</title>

  <authorgroup>
    <author>
      <firstname>Jérôme</firstname>
      <surname>PANSANEL</surname>
      <email>jerome.pansanel@iphc.cnrs.fr</email>
    </author>
  </authorgroup>

  <copyright>
    <year>2009-2012</year>
    <holder>CNRS</holder>
  </copyright>

  <date>13 Feb 2012</date>
  <releaseinfo>0.9.1</releaseinfo>

  <abstract>
    <para>
The Mychem Handbook is a documentation for the
Mychem software. The Mychem software provides a set
of functions for handling chemical data within MySQL.
Mychem v0.9.1 is based on Open Babel version 2.3.0 (or any
later version).
    </para>
  </abstract>

  <keywordset>
    <keyword>MySQL</keyword>
    <keyword>Chemistry</keyword>
    <keyword>Chemical database</keyword>
    <keyword>Chemical structure</keyword>
    <keyword>Structure search</keyword>
  </keywordset>

  <legalnotice>
    <para>
Redistribution and use in source (XML DocBook) and 'compiled' forms (SGML,
HTML, PDF, PostScript, RTF and so forth) with or without modification, are
permitted provided that the following conditions are met:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
Redistributions of source code (SGML DocBook) must retain the above copyright
notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer as the first lines
of this file unmodified.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
Redistributions in compiled form (transformed to other DTDs, converted to PDF,
PostScript, RTF and other formats) must reproduce the above copyright notice,
this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>

    <para>
This documentation is provided "as is" and any express or implied warranties,
including, but not limited to, the implied warranties of merchantability and
fitness for a particular purpose are disclaimed. In no event shall the Mychem
documentation be liable for any direct, indirect, incidental, special,
exemplary, or consequential damages (including, but not limited to, procurement
of substitute goods or services; loss of use, data, or profits; or business
interruption) however caused and on any theory of liability, whether in
contract, strict liability, or tort (including negligence or otherwise) arising
in any way out of the use of this documentation, even if advised of the
possibility of such damage.
    </para>
  </legalnotice>

</bookinfo>

<toc>
  <title>Contents</title>
</toc>

&introduction;
&usingMychem;
&commandReference;
&credits;
&installation;
&troubleshooting;
&sdfscript;
&db-manager;
&molecule.formats;

</book>
